<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble petition of divers well-affected persons, delivered the 6th day of July, 1659. To the supreme authority, the Parliament of the Common-vvealth of England. With the Parliaments answer thereunto, and sense thereupon.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E989_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862773</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862773</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114949</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86768)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114949)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E989[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble petition of divers well-affected persons, delivered the 6th day of July, 1659. To the supreme authority, the Parliament of the Common-vvealth of England. With the Parliaments answer thereunto, and sense thereupon.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Brewster, at the three Bibles in Pauls Church-yard, at the West end,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Supporting parliamentary rule over monarchy.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114949:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HUMBLE PETITION OF DIVERS Well-affected Perſons, <hi>DELIVERED</hi> The 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>July,</hi> 1659. TO THE <hi>SUPREME AUTHORITY,</hi> THE PARLIAMENT OF THE Common-vvealth OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> With the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and Senſe thereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Brewcter,</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the Weſt end, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:114949:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114949:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Supream Authority, THE</hi> Parliament <hi>of the</hi> Commonwealth <hi>of</hi> England. The Humble Petition of divers well-affected Perſons.</head>
            <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
            <p>THat your Petitioners have for many years ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the breathings and longings of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after Reſt and Settlement, and that upon miſtaken grounds they have been ready even to ſacrifice and yield up part of their own undoubted right, to follow after an appearance of it.</p>
            <p>And your Petitioners do daily ſee the bad effects of long continued diſtractions, in the ruines and decayes of Trade Forraign and Domeſtique; And in the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages that are taken to make Confederacies to involve the Nation in Blood and Confuſion, under pretence of procuring a Settlement.</p>
            <p>That it hath been the practice of all Nations upon the ſubverſion of any form of Government, to provide im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114949:3"/>a new conſtitution, ſuitable to their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; with certain ſucceſſions and deſcents, that ſo both their Law-givers and Magiſtrates, might uſe their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Truſts, according to the eſtabliſhed conſtitution; and the Peoples mindes be ſetled ſecure, and free from attempts of intraducing ſeveral forms of Governments, according to the variety of their fancies, or corrupt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</p>
            <p>That God hath preſerved this Nation wonderfully without example many years, ſince the diſſolution of the old form of Government, by King, Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, there having been no fundamental Conſtitutions of any kind duly ſetled, nor any certain ſucceſſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for the Legiſlative power; but even at this inſtant, if by any ſudden ſickneſs, deſign or force, any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable numbers of your perſons ſhould be rendered inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of meeting in Parliament, The Commonwealth were without form of ſucceſſive Legiſlature or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, and left to the mercy of the ſtrongeſt faction. Yet we have reaſon to remember in theſe years of unſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the expreſſible ſufferings of this Nation, in their ſtrength, wealth, honour, liberty, and all things condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to their well-being; And we have like reaſon now, ſadly to apprehend the unpending ruine; And we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcern a poſſibility of your Honours unanimous, and expeditious proceedings towards our Countries preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and relief from its heavy preſſures, whileſt your mindes are not ſetled in any known Conſtitution of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment or fundamental Orders: according to which, all Lawes ſhould be made; but diverſe or contrary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts may be proſecuted upon different apprehenſions of the Juſtice and Prudence of different forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, though all with good intentions.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114949:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Petitioners therefore conceiving no remedy ſo effectual againſt the preſent dangers, as the ſettlement of the peoples mindes, and putting them into actual ſecurity of their properties and liberties, by a due eſtabliſhment of the Conſtitution under which they may evidently appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend their certain enjoyment of them; and thereupon, a return of their Trade and free Commerce, without thoſe continual feares, that maketh ſuch frequent ſtops in Trade, to the ruine of thouſands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And your Petitioners alſo obſerving, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the late Kings Sonne, is cryed up, and promoted daily, upon pretence, that there will be nothing but confuſion and Tyranny, until he come to govern; and that ſuch as declare for a Commonwealth, are for Annarchy and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and can never agree amongſt themſelves, what they would have.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Upon ſerious thoughts of the premiſes, your Petitioners do preſume with all humility, and ſubmiſsion to your Wiſdom to offer to your Honours, their Principalls and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſalls concerning the Government of this Nation: Whereupon, they humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, a juſt and prudent Government ought to be eſtabliſhed,</hi> viz.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114949:4"/>
            <p n="1">I. That the Conſtitution of the Civil Government of <hi>England</hi> by King, Lords, and Commons, being diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, whatever new Conſtitution or Government can be made or ſettled according to any Rule of righteouſneſs, It can be no other then a wiſe Order or Method, into which the free Peoples Deputies ſhall be formed for the making of their Lawes; and taking Care for their Common ſafety and welfare in the execution of them: For, the exerciſe of all juſt authority over a free People, ought (under God) to ariſe from their own Conſent.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the Government of a free People ought to be ſo ſettled, that the Governours and Governed may have the ſame Intereſt in preſerving the Government, and each others Proprieties and Liberties reſpectively; That being the onely ſure foundation of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth's Unity, Peace, Strength, and Proſperity.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That there cannot be an Union of the Intereſts of a whole Nation in the Government, where thoſe who ſhall ſometimes Govern, be not alſo ſometimes in the Condition of the Governed; otherwiſe the Governours will not be in a capacity to feel the weight of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, nor the Governed to enjoy the advantages of it: And then it will be the intereſt of the <hi>Major</hi> part to deſtroy the Government; as much as it will be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>Minor</hi> part to preſerve it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114949:4"/>
            <p n="4">IV. That there is no ſecurity that the Supream Authority ſhall not fall into factions, and be led by their private Intereſt to keep themſelves alwayes in power, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Government to their private advantages; If that Supream Authority be ſetled in any Single Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly whatſoever, That ſhall have the entire power of Propounding, Debating, and reſolving Laws.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That the Soveraign Authority in every Government of what kind ſoever, ought to be certain in its perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Succeſſions, Revolutions or Deſcents: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out poſſibility (by the Judgement of humane prudence) of a death or failer of its being, becauſe the whole forme of the Government is diſſolved, if that ſhould happen, and the people in the utmoſt imminent danger of an abſolute Tyranny, or a War amongſt themſelves; or Rapine and confuſion. And therefore where the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is Popular, the Aſſemblies in whom reſide the Supream Authority, ought never to die or diſſolve: though the perſons be annually Changing: neither ought they to truſt the Soveraign care of the ſtrength and ſafety of the people our of their own hands, by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing a Vacation to themſelves, leſt thoſe that ſhould be truſted be in love with ſuch Great Authority, and aſpire to be their Maſters, or elſe fear an Account, and ſeek the diſſolution of the Common-wealth to avoyd it.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. That it ought to be declared as a Fundamental Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Conſtitution of this Common-wealth, that the Parliament being the Supream Legiſlative Power, is intended only for the exerciſe of all thoſe Acts of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114949:5"/>Authority that are proper and peculiar unto the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Power; and to provide for a Magiſtracy, unto whom ſhould appertain the whole Executive Power of the Lawes: and no Caſe either Civil or Criminal to be Judged in Parliament, ſaving that the laſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals in all Caſes, where Appeals ſhall be thought fit to be admitted, be only unto the Popular Aſſembly; and alſo that unto them be referred the Judgement of all Magiſtrates in Caſes of Male Adminiſtrations in their Offices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in proſecution of theſe Principles, Your Petitioners Humbly propoſe for the Settlement of this Commonwealth, that it be Ordained,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Parliament or the Supreme Authority of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>be choſen by the free People, to repreſent them with as much equality as may be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That a Parliament of</hi> England <hi>ſhall conſiſt of two Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, the leſſer of about three hundred, in whom ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the entire power of conſulting, debating, and propounding Lawes: the other, to conſiſt of a farre greater number, in whom ſhall reſt the ſole power of reſolving all Lawes ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the free People of</hi> England, <hi>in their reſpective diviſions at certain dayes and places appointed, ſhall for ever annually chooſe one third part to each Aſſembly, to enter into their Authority, at certain dayes appointed: the ſame dayes, the Authority of a third of each of the ſaid Aſſemblies to ceaſe, onely in the laying the firſt Foundation in this</hi> Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths <hi>Conſtitution: the whole number of both the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies to be choſen by the People reſpectively,</hi> (viz.) <hi>One third of each Aſſembly to be choſen for one year, One third for two years, and one third for three years.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:114949:5"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That ſuch as ſhall be choſen, having ſerved their appointed time in either of the ſaid Aſſemblies of Parliament ſhall not be capeable to ſerve in the ſame aſſembly during ſome convenient intervall or vacation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That the Legiſlative power doe wholy refer the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Laws unto the Magiſtracy, according to the ſixth principle herein mentioned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That in reſpect to Religion and Chriſtian liberty, It be ordained that the Chriſtian Religion by the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ſucceeding Parliaments, be taught, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgated to the Nation, and publique Preachers thereof maintained; and that all that ſhall profeſſe the ſaid Religion, though of different perſwaſions in parts of the Doctrine, or Diſcipline thereof, be equally protected in the peaceable profeſſion, &amp; publique exerciſe of the ſame; and be equally capeable of all elections, Magiſtracies, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments in the commonwealth, according to the order of the ſame.</hi> Provided alwaies, <hi>that the publique exerciſe of no Religion contrary to Chriſtianity be tollorated: nor the publique exerciſe of any Religion, though pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly Chriſtian, grounded upon, or incorporated into the intereſt of any Forraign State or Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe your Petitioners humbly conceive, to be the Eſſentials of the form of a free Commonwealth, which if they were made fit for practiſe by your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners appointing the numbers, times, places, and all other neceſſary circumſtances, and ſetled as the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Orders of the Commonwealth, would na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally diſpoſe thoſe that ſhould hereafter be choſen into the Parliaments, from the love of their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to ſeek the common good being obliged by the conſtitutions here humbly offered to partake
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114949:6"/>with the whole body of the people, of the good or evil that ſhall happen to the Commonwealth, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no probable temptations or means left, to compaſs any private or factious ends in matters Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious or Civil, And your Petitioners cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine a greater ſecurity for the cauſe and intereſt contended for with ſuch effuſion of blood, Then by diſpoſing the free people into this kind of order, whereby the ſame cauſe would become their common intereſt. Yet if your Honours ſhould think it neceſſary or convenient for ſecuring the minds of ſuch as are doubtful, and jealous, that the people may betray their own liberties; There may be inſerted into the fundamental orders of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, theſe following Expedients, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I That for ſecuring the government of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, &amp; of the Religious and Civil freedom of the good people thereof, it may be for ever eſteemed &amp; judged Treaſon againſt the Commonwealth, for any member of either Aſſembly of Parliament, or any other perſon whatſoever to move or propoſe in either of the ſaid Aſſemblies, the reſtitution of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Government, or the introduction of any ſingle Perſon to be chief Magiſtrate of <hi>England,</hi> or the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that part of the fundamental order herein contained that concerns the equal freedom and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Religious perſons of different perſwaſions.</p>
            <p n="2">II That about the number of twelve perſons of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114949:6"/>moſt undoubted fidelity and integrity, may be au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed and impowred for ſome certain number of yeers next enſuing to ſeize, apprehend, and in ſafe cuſtody to detain any perſon or perſons whatſoever till he or they be in due form of law, delivered as is hereafter ſpecified; That ſhall move or propoſe in either of the ſaid Aſſemblies of Parliament the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Kingly Government, or the Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of any ſingle perſon to be chief Magiſtrate of this Commonwealth, or the alteration of that part of the fundamental order herein contained, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the equal freedom, and protection of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, of different perſwaſions. But for no other matter or cauſe whatſoever; And when it ſhall happen that any perſon or perſons ſhall be are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted or ſeized for any of the cauſes aforeſaid, in manner aforeſaid; a Commiſſion <hi>of Oyer and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner</hi> may iſſue forth in due form of Law, unto the ſaid Twelve or any Six of them to proceed in due form of law, within one moneth after the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of any ſuch perſon or perſons: to the arraignment and publique trial of every ſuch perſon or perſons, and upon the legal conviction of him or them by the teſtimony of two ſufficient witneſſes of any of the Treaſons herein declared, to condemn to the pains of death; and to cauſe the ſame Judgment to be duly executed, and the keeper or keepers of the great ſeal of England that ſhall be for the time being may be authoriſed and required from time to time during the Term of yeers to iſſue out Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions unto the ſaid twelve or any ſix of them authorizing them to proceed as aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114949:7"/>
            <p>And if your Honours ſhall further judge it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, the fundamental orders of the Government may be conſented unto or ſubſcribed, by the people themſelves, if their expreſs pact ſhall be eſteemed any additional ſecurity; other Nations upon the like occaſions of expulſion of their Kings, having taken the peoples oathes againſt their returning, And the ſame may be proclaimed as often as our Anceſtors provided for the proclaiming of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and any further ſecurity alſo added, if any can be found amongſt men, that hath a foundation in juſtice.</p>
            <p>Now your Petitioners having with humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to your grave wiſdomes, thus declared their apprehenſions of the preſent condition of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted Nation, and the only effectual means un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God to prevent the impending miſchiefs; They do moſt humbly pray,</p>
            <p>That ſuch ſpeedy Conſiderations may be had of the premiſes as the Condition of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on requires, and that ſuch a method may be ſetled for the debating, and conſulting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Government, that your wiſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults may be ſeaſonable for the healing all the breaches of the Commonwealth and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing ſure foundations of Freedom, Juſtice, Peace, and Unity.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>And your Petitioners ſhall alwayes pray,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114949:7"/>
            <head>Wedneſday, July the 6. 1659.</head>
            <p>The houſe being informed that divers Gentlemen were at the door with a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, they were called in, and one of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners in the Behalf of himſelf and the reſt ſaid, we humbly preſent you a petition, to which we might have had many thouſand hands, but the matter rather deſerves your ſerious conſideration then any publique at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, and therefore we do humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to this honourable Houſe: which after the petitioners were withdrawn was read and was entituled, The humble Petition of divers well affected perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Petitioners have the thankes of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners were again called in and <hi>Mr. Speaker</hi> gave them this anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Houſe hath read over your Petition, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114949:8"/>find it without any private end, and only for publique intereſt, And I am commanded to let you know that it lyeth much upon them to make ſuch a ſettlement, as may be moſt for the good of poſterity. And they are about that worke, and intend to goe forward with it with as much expedition as may be, And for your parts they have commanded me to give you thankes: and in their names I do give you the thanks of this Houſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Tho. St. Nicholas</hi> Clerke of the Parliament.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114949:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
